<!-- $Id -->
<chapter>
	<!-- Source: ##UserIssues section of the online help  -->
	<title>Entering and managing issues</title>
	<para>Scarab has a very dynamic issue management strategy. Committing, tracking and modifying issues is a simple process. Scarab has the following issue management features&nbsp;:</para>
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				<emphasis role="bold">Relations&nbsp;:</emphasis> Scarab can track relationships between issues. Dependencies between issues can be flagged and tracked through either the issue entry process or while reviewing one or multiple issues. </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				<emphasis role="bold">Change tracking&nbsp;:</emphasis> All changes made along with information about the user who made the change, when the change was made and any comments committed along with the change are tracked with the issue.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				<emphasis role="bold">Comment viewing and editing:&nbsp;:</emphasis> All comments made to the issue are tracked. Comments allow support or other type conversations to be viewable and editable by any parties interested in the progress of an issue. </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				<emphasis role="bold">Save frequently entered information:&nbsp;:</emphasis> The issue entry template feature allows you to create a frequently used set of data points for attributes in a template. When a template is used, the issue entry form is pre-populated and the user can alter information as needed.</para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	<sect1>
		<title>Entering an issue</title>
		<para>After selecting your issue type and the Enter new link from the left navigation you can enter values for the available attributes. Each attribute will have either a drop down box with options to select from or a text entry form for you to enter text. All attributes with an asterisks (*) beside the title must have values before saving the issue.</para>
		<para>If duplication tracking is active, entering an issue becomes a three step process. The first step is to define a subset of attributes that will be used to check for duplicates in the database once you have used the button. The second step is to review all possible duplicates and determine what action to perform (see Duplicates for more information on duplicate management). The third step is to enter values for the remaining attributes.</para>
		<para>While you are entering the issue you can attach a relevant file using the  same form. Attaching a file helps you and others to easily share relevant information or patches. For more information on adding attachments see Attachments..</para>
		<para>Before submitting your issue you can select where in the application you would like to go next. Each option submits the issue and takes you to one of the following functional areas:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Assign issue</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>View this issue</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Start page</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Return to home</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
