<chapter>
	<title>Scarab development with Netbeans</title>
	<sect1>
		<title>Getting the Scarab sources</title>
		<para>
			The current implementation of a Subversion client for Netbeans (code named &quot;teepee&quot;, available from <ulink url="http://subversion.netbeans.org/">http://subversion.netbeans.org/</ulink>) is only a prototype.
			So, at the moment, you need to use another client to check the sources out of the Scarab Subversion repository.
			If you use Windows as your development environment, you'll probably want to use <ulink url="http://tortoisesvn.tigris.org/">TortoiseSVN</ulink> - another Tigris project.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Getting the Mevenide plug-in (Maven-Netbeans integration)</title>
		<para>Your best option to develop Scarab in Netbeans is certainly to use the Mevenide plug-in (which is, by the way, much more stable and functional in Netbeans than in Eclipse, not to mention JBuilder).</para>
		<para>Download Mevenide for Netbeans at this URL: <ulink url="http://mevenide.codehaus.org/mevenide-netbeans-project/index.html">http://mevenide.codehaus.org/mevenide-netbeans-project/index.html</ulink>
		</para>
		<para>You will get a ZIP file with 16 nbm (Netbeans modules) inside. Unzip the file to a temporary directory.</para>
		<sect2>
			<title>Installing the Mevenide plug-in</title>
			<tip>
				<simpara>If you are familiar with Netbeans modules installation, you will probably want to skip this section.</simpara>
			</tip>
			<simpara>In the Tools menu, choose Update Center</simpara>
			<screenshot>
				<graphic fileref="images/netbeans01.png"/>
			</screenshot>
			<simpara>Check 'Install Manually Downloaded Modules (.nbm Files)'</simpara>
			<screenshot>
				<graphic fileref="images/netbeans02.png"/>
			</screenshot>
			<simpara>Use the 'Add...' button to add the 16 files you have downloaded.</simpara>
			<screenshot>
				<graphic fileref="images/netbeans03.png"/>
			</screenshot>
			<simpara>Just click 'Next >'.</simpara>
			<screenshot>
				<graphic fileref="images/netbeans04.png"/>
			</screenshot>
			<simpara>You will have to accept the different licences. The modules are then ready for installation.</simpara>
			<screenshot>
				<graphic fileref="images/netbeans05.png"/>
			</screenshot>
			<simpara>View the certificate (there is only one here) and click 'Finish' to install the modules.</simpara>
			<screenshot>
				<graphic fileref="images/netbeans06.png"/>
			</screenshot>
			<simpara>You need now to restart Netbeans to use the Mevenide plug-in you have just installed.</simpara>
			<screenshot>
				<graphic fileref="images/netbeans07png"/>
			</screenshot>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Scarab in-place development</title>
		<simpara>Accessing the Scarab project is now as easy as it can be. In the File menu, choose 'Open Project...'</simpara>
		<screenshot>
			<graphic fileref="images/netbeans08.png"/>
		</screenshot>
		<simpara>Choose the directory in which you checked out Scarab from the Subversion repository.</simpara>
		<screenshot>
			<graphic fileref="images/netbeans09.png"/>
		</screenshot>
		<simpara>There it is !</simpara>
		<screenshot>
			<graphic fileref="images/netbeans10.png"/>
		</screenshot>
		<simpara>You have direct access to Scarab custom Maven goals by right-clicking the Scarab project.</simpara>
		<screenshot>
			<graphic fileref="images/netbeans11.png"/>
		</screenshot>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
