<!-- $Id$ -->
<chapter>
	<title>Integrating Scarab and your IDE</title>
	<sect1>
		<title>Eclipse</title>
		<simpara>An interesting way to bring Scarab information into Eclipse is probably to use an RSS reader, for example <ulink url="http://morphine.sourceforge.net/presence/projects/rss/index.html">Eclipse RSS Reader</ulink>. Let us use this plugin as an example.</simpara>
		<simpara>Say you want to keep an eye on the history of the PACS1 issue in Scarab. In the bottom right corner of the issue page in Scarab, you have RSS and ATOM links.</simpara>
		<screenshot>
			<graphic fileref="images/pacs1-rss1.fr.png"/>
		</screenshot>
		<simpara>Copy the URL in the RSS link.</simpara>
		<screenshot>
			<graphic fileref="images/pacs1-rss2.fr.png"/>
		</screenshot>
		<simpara>Now, in Eclipse, create a new RSS channel.</simpara>
		<screenshot>
			<graphic fileref="images/pacs1-rss3.png"/>
		</screenshot>
		<simpara>Paste the issue RSS feed URL and click &quot;Load&quot;.</simpara>
		<screenshot>
			<graphic fileref="images/pacs1-rss4.png"/>
		</screenshot>
		<simpara>There is only one translator available for this feed format, so you may proceed.</simpara>
		<screenshot>
			<graphic fileref="images/pacs1-rss5.png"/>
		</screenshot>
		<simpara>Now you must choose a project and a file name for your RSS feed.</simpara>
		<screenshot>
			<graphic fileref="images/pacs1-rss6.png"/>
		</screenshot>
		<simpara>The RSS appears now among your project resources in the Package Explorer.</simpara>
		<screenshot>
			<graphic fileref="images/pacs1-rss7.png"/>
		</screenshot>
		<simpara>When you click the feed, you get a new window with the history. The &quot;Browse&quot; link brings you back to Scarab in the issue page.</simpara>
		<screenshot>
			<graphic fileref="images/pacs1-rss8.png"/>
		</screenshot>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Netbeans</title>
		<abstract>
			<para>A NetBeans plugin allows to include Scarab issues in the to-do list.</para>
			<para>This plug-in (.nbm) is currently available from the NetBeans tracker at this URL: <ulink url="http://tasklist.netbeans.org/issues/show_bug.cgi?id=69572">http://tasklist.netbeans.org/issues/show_bug.cgi?id=69572</ulink>
			</para>
		</abstract>
		<important>
			<para>This plug-in only works with the current Scarab development version (i.e., trunk, HEAD); it doesn't work in the latest stable release (milestone 20).</para>
		</important>
		<simpara>[This section to be written.]</simpara>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
