<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>

<properties>
    <title>How To Build Scarab Docs</title>
    <author email="epugh@upstate.com">Eric Pugh</author>
</properties>

<body>

<section name="How To Build Scarab Docs">
<p>
	The Scarab documenation is written using both xdoc and docbook formats.  This documentation is 
	generated by  <a href="http://maven.apache.org">Maven</a>.  If you haven't used Maven before, 
	follow the <a href="http://maven.apache.org/start/index.html">Getting Started</a> directions.
</p>

	<subsection name="Generating Maven Managed Docs">
	<p>
	Documentation should all be written in the xdoc format, and stored under the /xdocs directory.  When you
	are ready to generate the documentation, you can run Maven's site generation goal via 'maven site'.  If you don't
	want to bother to run the unit tests, then run 'maven site -Dmaven.test.skip=true'.  This will generate all
	the site documentation, as well as the FAQ, Javadocs, and various code analysis reports in the directory "/target/docs".
	</p>
	<p>
	We use a Tasks plugin from <a href="http://maven-plugins.sourceforge.net/maven-tasks-plugin/">Maven-Plugins</a>
	to generate the roadmap document.  This plugin should download automatically and install.  If not, look at the
	directions <a href="http://maven-plugins.sourceforge.net/installing.html">here</a>.
	</p>
	<p>
	We use a Findbugs plugin from <a href="http://maven-plugins.sourceforge.net/maven-findbugs-plugin/">Maven-Plugins</a>
	to look for common errors.  This plugin should download automatically and install.  If not, look at the
	directions <a href="http://maven-plugins.sourceforge.net/installing.html">here</a>.
	</p>
	<p>
	We use a StatCVS plugin from <a href="http://statcvs-xml.berlios.de/">StatCVS</a>
	to generate statistics on CVS.  This plugin should download automatically and install.  It requires CVS executable
	to be in your path.  If you have TortoiseCVS installed on windows, then just add that directory to your path!  The
	CVS.exe in the TortoiseCVS directory works fine.
	</p>		
	</subsection>
</section>
</body>
</document>
