<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>

 <properties>
  <title>Scarab: Flexible artifact management</title>
  <author email="epugh@opensourceconnections.com">Eric Pugh</author>
 </properties>

 <body>

 <section name="What is Scarab?">

 <p>
    Scarab is a highly customizable artifact tracking system supporting
    the following feature set:
 </p>

 <ul>
     <li><strong>Standard features</strong><br/>
         data entry, queries,
         reports, notifications to interested parties, 
         collaborative accumulation of comments,
         dependency tracking.<p/>
      </li>
     <li><strong>Fully customizable</strong><br/>
         Scarab has fully and free
         customizable and unlimited numbers of
         <ul>
           <li>Modules (e.g. your various projects)</li>
           <li>Artifact types (e.g. "Defect", "Enhancement", "Requirement", etc)</li>
           <li>Attributes (e.g. "Operating System", "Status", "Priority", etc)</li>
           <li>Attribute options</li>
         </ul>
         <p>
         All aspects of your artefact management can be defined
         on a per Module basis so that each of your modules is
         configured for your specific tracking requirements.
         </p>
     </li>
     <li><strong>Multi lingual</strong><br/>
         Scarab uses java resource bundle technology and is shipped
         with the language localizations for de, en, es, fr, it, ja, 
         ko, nl, pl, pt, ru and zh. The used languages are all available
         simultaneously. Users can choose their individual language
         based on their browser language preference settings.<p/>
     </li>
     <li><strong>Based on application server technologies</strong><br/>
         Scarab is built using Java Servlet technology for speed, 
         scalability, maintainability, and ease of installation.<p/>
     </li>
     <li><strong>Import/Export interface via XML</strong><br/>
         That allows an easy migration
         from other tracking systems (e.g. Bugzilla).<p/>
     </li>
     <li><strong>Modular code design</strong><br/>
         That allows manageable modifications of
         existing and new features over time.<p/>
     </li>
     <li><strong>Integrated customization UI</strong><br/>
         Scarab is fully customizable through a set of administrative 
         pages.<p/>
     </li>
     <li><strong>Easily modifiable UI look and feel</strong><br/>
         <p/>
     </li>
     <li><strong>Integrateable</strong><br/>
         Scarab can be integrated into larger systems by 
         re-implementing key interfaces.<p/>
     </li>
     <li><strong>Self contained</strong><br/>
        Scarab is a ready to use issue management system.<p/>
     </li>
 </ul>          

</section>

<section name="Where do I get releases?">

  <p>
    There are two types of downloads. There is the source download available from the Subversion <a href="http://svn.collab.net/viewcvs/scarab">repository</a> and the stable releases from the <a href="http://scarab.tigris.org/servlets/ProjectDownloadList">Project Download List</a>.  
  </p>
  <p>
    You can also download a nightly built from <a href="http://apache.org/~jon/scarab/nightly/">here</a>.  
  </p>
</section>

<section name="How do I contribute ...?">

<subsection name="Scarab developers/users Community">
<p>
If you want to actively contribute, give feedback or send bug fixes,
then please join the Scarab.Tigris.org community by <a
href="http://scarab.tigris.org/servlets/Join">registering</a> with the site and then <a
href="http://scarab.tigris.org/servlets/ProjectMembershipRequest">requesting</a> an 
<strong>Observer</strong> role within the Scarab project.
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="Mailing Lists">
<p>To get involved with the development of Scarab, please 
join the developer's <a href="http://scarab.tigris.org/servlets/ProjectMailingListList">mailing list</a>.
</p>

<p>
    The first thing you should send when you join the list is to post an
    introduction message that tells the group:
</p>

<ul>
    <li>Who you are</li>
    <li>A link to a picture, if ya have one</li>
    <li>Your interest in Issue Tracking</li>
    <li>The role you would like to play in the project (e.g., do you want to just 
        discuss ideas, write code, do UI design, or be an early users?), and</li>
    <li>The rough level of effort you expect to put (e.g., mainly lurking, a few 
        postings a week, a few evenings, several hours a week, this is part of my 
        full-time job).</li>
</ul>
</subsection>
<subsection name="Getting Started">
<p>
The first place to start off with developing on Scarab is to download
the <a href="http://svn.collab.net/viewcvs/scarab">SVN tree</a>
and explore the documentation, build system and code that is there
already. Build a "target" sandbox, startup Tomcat and explore the
templates that are already there. Analyze the database design and look
at the files in the src/sql directory (the default-data and sample-data)
files are very helpful. The README.txt file documents everything
necessary to get a Scarab installation up and running. It's easy.
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="Submitting Issues">
<p>
After searching the issue tracker and you really do have an original problem to report, 
then please report it using our 
<a href="http://www.solitone.org/scarab/issues/">issue tracker</a>. Register and
create a new account. Make sure to request a DEVELOPER role. Please 
include a detailed message that describes the problem (make it as easy
as possible to understand), how to reproduce the problem and a stack
trace if one is generated.  Make sure the the email address you register with is
subscribed to the issues <a href="http://scarab.tigris.org/servlets/ProjectMailingListList">mailing list</a> so that emails generated by Scarab are
properly sent to the mailing list.
</p>

<p>
<strong>NOTE: Please do not use the issue tracker to create
test issues</strong>. You can use our <a href="http://www.saxess.com/en/components/scarab/testserver.page">runbox hosted by Saxess</a>
to create as many test issues as you want.
</p>

<p>
If the issue tracker is unavailable or you have a problem with it,
please contact <a href="mailto:dev@scarab.tigris.org">the developers</a>
and let them know.
</p>
</subsection>

</section>

 </body>
 </document>
