<!-- $Id -->
<chapter>
	<title>Introduction</title>
	<sect1>
		<!-- Source: the ##Introduction section in the online help -->
		<title>What is Scarab&nbsp;?</title>
		<para>Scarab is a highly configurable issue tracking tool that can be used for all types of projects: technical and non-technical alike. Because all parameters in the system are configurable, this tool meets the needs of the project as well as the individual user. Each implementation can be configured directly to the workflow processes of the project through the definition of issue types and attributes. The user interface is designed to be accessible and constant: once you become familiar with the look and feel you will find new processes quick to master.</para>
		<para>Scarab provides a robust set of tools for issue management&nbsp;:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis role="bold">Issue entry&nbsp;:</emphasis> The issue entry process is designed to help users create meaningful issues and avoid duplication.  Attributes are used to describe issues and to check the issue database for similar entries. If any duplicates are found, the user has the opportunity to review potential duplicates, add comments to like issues or modify their issue before committing it to the database. </para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis role="bold">Templates for issue entry&nbsp;:</emphasis> Frequently entered issue criteria can be saved in templates for speedy entry. Files can be attached to an issue, and are tracked directly with their issue. Users can add and edit comments to issues as needed. Users can access and review the complete issue history while viewing an issue. </para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis role="bold">Issue query&nbsp;:</emphasis> Accessing issues in the database is simple using the query feature. Users can easily find, access and modify issues individually or in groups. The advanced query feature allows the user to create detailed issue searches, specifying values for multiple attributes and limiting their search to specific date or issue number ranges. The Custom Query feature allows the user to search by text string-the user can specify a set of information to compare against issues in the database. Frequently used queries can be saved and easily run.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis role="bold">Reports&nbsp;:</emphasis> The robust reports interface allows the user to create and save reports. Reports provide customizable and meaningful metrics.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis role="bold">Email notifications&nbsp;:</emphasis> As important events occur, email is generated and sent to all parties associated with the event. Alert emails contain links to views of the event.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>Scarab is written in Java and based on web technologies. Scarab stores its informations in a database, often MySQL but other databases such as Oracle and PostgreSQL are supported.</para>
		<sect2>
			<title>How does Scarab differ from other issue-tracking systems&nbsp;?</title>
			<para>Scarab is highly customisable. Scarab has no predefined or hard-coded workflow (that would define what happens as an issue changes from the 'Open' to the 'Closed' status. There are no predefined artefact types (such as bug report, improvement, etc.) You are completely free to define your issue types the way that suits you best. Scarab may be less easy to understand and use at the beginning but you will get a tool that suits your needs better at the end.</para>
			<para>Most other issue tracking systems (open-source or commercial) have an issue processing logic that is embedded in the application. This means that you are often caught in the logic defined by these systems. Scarab does not limit you that way.</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Scarab history</title>
		<para>To stay short, let's say that Scarab was born from the passion of a highly talented developer&nbsp;: Jon Scott Stevens. Jon was a key figure in the Apache Jakarta project, where he played a major role in the Velocity and Turbine projects.</para>
		<para>His aim was to design and develop a compelling replacement for Bugzilla.</para>
		<para>CollabNet gave him an opportunity to develop this software in open-source &mdash; but also to integrate this tool in their collaborative development suite.</para>
		<para>Today, CollabNet is no longer the driving force behind the development of Scarab; they left this role to a small team of developers from around the world but continue to provide support and useful advice on certain occasions.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<!-- Source: Scarab home page at http://scarab.tigris.org -->
		<title>Scarab functionality at a glance</title>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>A full set of functions such as those found in other issue tracking systems&nbsp;: issue entry, queries, reports, event notification, collaborative accumulation of comments, dependency tracking.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>On top of these standard functions, Scarab provides an unlimited number of fully configurable modules (your projects), of artefact types (Defect, Improvement request, Requirements,...), of Attributes (Operating system, Status, Priority, etc.), of Attribute options (P1, P2, P3) that can all be defined on a per-module basis, so that any module can be configured for specific needs..</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Import/Export interface via XML&nbsp;: allows an easy migration from other tracking systems (e.g. Bugzilla).</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Modular code design: allows manageable modifications of existing and new features over time.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Integrated customization UI&nbsp;: Scarab is fully customizable through a set of administrative pages.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Easily modifiable UI look and feel.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Integration&nbsp;:Scarab can be integrated into larger systems by re-implementing key interfaces.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Based on application server technologies&nbsp;:Scarab is built using Java Servlet technology for speed, scalability, maintainability, and ease of installation.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Sharing the information and tracking projects</title>
		<para>The success of any project depends on managing and solving problems.  How you use the tools will be dependent upon how your project is organized and your planned workflow processes.  You can use the tools as a knowledge sharing device and a means of tracking and managing the health of your project.</para>
		<sect2>
			<title>Sharing information in a project</title>
			<para>Information captured within Scarab can be highly effective for many areas within a project. Because Scarab is so highly configurable, knowledge resources can be customized to the needs of each discipline within an organization. Tracking a feature across discipline lines can be done by copying issues and creating dependencies between them.</para>
			<para>For instance, Project Go has issue types organized by milestone within the feature lifecycle. Project Go has the following issue types: Planning, Development, Testing, Release management and Support. New features are entered in the Planning issue type where they are processed till ready for development. At that point, the issue is copied to Development, Release management and Testing issue types and all copies are set to blocked by the Development issue. All actors have a full description of the feature, including all conversations involved in creating the specifications. Since all issues have interdependencies, monitoring efforts across the discipline lines is an easy process. Blocking all the issues by the Development issue means that none of them can be closed till the development cycle has completed, but each group can continue to work based on what is happening with the development project. For example, documentation may be a part of the release management cycle. Writers can track the features in development and track their documentation efforts in their own issue with links to the development issue. After the feature has been released to the users, support can track incoming issues and easily access information about the feature through any of the issue types and be able to link to other areas quickly through the issue history. </para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Tracking the health of a project</title>
			<para>Scarab can assist in tracking and assessing the health of a project. If your project is experiencing a particular type of concern you need to track, Scarab can help you do this through a series of processes.</para>
			<para>For example, Project Go has just added a new database and developers are concerned that the new database will cause significant performance problems. While running routine reports and queries, the project lead has determined that there is, indeed, a performance issue possibly associated with the new database. It is determined that fixing this problem is top priority and critical to the success of the project. To facilitate work on this problem, the project owner has created an issue entry template and series of queries and reports. Users are asked to use the template and enter specific information about what they have found in a description attribute. The template is used to regularize information about issues. Using a saved query, project members can quickly access issues involving this concern and concentrate efforts in critical areas. Tracking the progress of resolving the performance problems can be done using reports. How to configure it for your needs can be confusing. This document is a suggested set of practices.</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
